The whole idea of vibe coding or
whatever flavors less vibe more coding
more vibe less coding
Yeah.
All of them boil down to the lack of
trust in the generated code. And it's
not because someone is evil and want to
like screw others. It's because it's
only natural for us to not give the full
attention to the code that something
else wrote comparing to the code that we
write.
My vibe coding's an interesting one
because with vibe coding we tend to
actually reduce the number of tests we
end up writing.
Yes.
And write code with a far greater lack
of integrity that we actually look to
validate.
Yeah.
Ourselves by by you know we tend not to
read. We
We trust in the AI doing it or we click
through and go oh yeah this kind of does
what it does.
And it looks good to me. The thing is
it's not because AI's in the mix. This
is also true for everything else.
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev. I am in well at the
AI Focus conference which for those who
um
maybe kind of like recognize the name
slightly it's it's a conference by
Matthias Karlsson uh again from uh from
JFocus.
It's a it's a spin-off.
It's a spin-off of JFocus. A conference
which we've both been to countless
times.
Yep.
And and um and joining me today uh
Baruch
Hi.
Uh Baruch Baruch Sadagursky.
Sadagursky.
Sadagursky. Oh it's kind of it's close.
Close close.
It's been a while. It's been a while. So
So Baruch we go back how many years? 10
15?
Um yeah I guess almost 20 like zero
turnaround early days.
Yeah. Yeah yeah.
You yeah yeah. Something like that.
About then you were in JFrog.
Yes. Early 2010s.
Early 2010s. Well well okay.
Oh I feel old Baruch now.
We are. We are.
We are.
We are. Yeah. Yeah.
And and and yeah, we were So, I saw you
at the speaker dinner yesterday here in
Stockholm. And I thought, "Oh, I need to
sit down with Brooke, chat to him, see
what he's see what he's talking about."
Yeah.
Um and and wow, we we was talking the
same language yesterday, man.
Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah, and that's
what I was excited about because I
thought about when I So, you're you're
working at Diesel and the idea of
spec-driven development. Um this is
something that obviously resonated with
me because I was thinking about this
idea of how can we make
code generation in AI accountable in an
easy way.
Mhm.
Right? Because in the end of the day,
the whole idea of vibe coding or
whatever flavors, less vibe, more
coding, more vibe, less coding, all of
them boil down to the lack of trust in
the generated code.
Mhm.
And it's not because someone is evil and
want to like screw others, it's because
it's only natural for us to
not
give the full attention to the code that
something else wrote comparing to the
code that we wrote.
Uh and with vibe coding is an
interesting one because with vibe coding
we tend to actually reduce the number of
tests we end up writing. Yes.
Um and write code with uh a far greater
lack of uh integrity that we actually
look to validate ourselves by by you
know, we tend not to read. We we
we trust in the AI doing it or we click
through and go, "Oh, yeah, this kind of
does what it does." And then I'm like,
"Okay."
Exactly.
Now, it's the the the the thing is it's
not because AI is in the mix. This is
also true for everything else. If we are
on the same team, you ask me to do a
code review, I look at your code. Well,
it looks okay to me. Looks good to me.
Let's ship it.
Mhm.
Now, this is terrible.
Yeah.
But, the And this is one of the reasons
why the software is terrible.
Mhm.
But, most of the software still works.
Yeah.
And it still works because, as you
mentioned, of integrity.
Mhm.
And the integrity that we are talking
about when we are two humans in the mix
is human integrity. Right? You are a
professional. You have standards.
I know that. And I trust you to an
extent.
Mhm.
I know that the code that you will give
me to a code review won't be absolute
garbage.
Well, it's been a while since I've
written code, but yeah, yeah. Okay.
Okay, I'll accept that.
Right? Now, how much worse it is when
code is generated by machine that has no
integrity, no standards, and usually
absolutely clueless about the code that
it's generating?
Yeah. Yeah.
So, it is much worse. But, we still
don't We won't apply any rigorous code
review because it's not a code. This is
not something we can do.
Yeah.
Right? So, the question is, how do we
automate this
integrity into the code that we see on
the other side?
Mhm.
And that was like my question to begin
with. And the way I thought about it,
well,
we have guardrails for code existing for
many decades.
Mhm.
And those guardrails are obviously
tests. Tests, of course. Right? So, what
if we put those guardrails in front up
front?
Mhm.
And then we let And then we don't care
that much about the quality of the code.
Mhm.
So, we can write tests, or we can
generate tests, somehow make sure that
we can trust those tests.
Mhm. Mhm.
And once we trust those tests, we will
have to trust the code that passes the
tests.
So, the the tests then
by from what you're saying there, the
tests become the most important thing,
the most important piece of code
effectively, because if you have bad
tests, you have bad code. If you have
good tests, you have
Yes, those are good guardrails. Those
are good guardrails. Now, obviously the
next question is, okay, but how does it
different? We don't want to write tests
either. So, we don't
So, if if the test will be generated, we
don't trust those tests as well.
So, in order to trust those tests, even
if they're generated, we need to read
them.
Yes.
And we don't want to read code.
Yes, as we just spoke about.
Not only that, if the test define what
our software do,
it's probably a wider circle of
stakeholders that need to
have a say in those guardrails, not only
developers.
People like product managers, like
business stakeholders, they definitely
not going to read tests.
Yeah, but they're actually the people
who have the probably the stronger
intention behind how something works.
They actually know what the software
should do. We just code monkeys that put
their intent
into code are going to be replaced with
other code monkeys that are going to put
Well, right, but but the really
important people in the mix are the
product managers, the business people,
and the customers.
Let me pull you up on something like you
said just before, you said we want
something to automate the test, we want
something to create tests because we
don't want to look at code, right? How
How true is that though? Right, because
I did a keynote at Devops um
a couple of weeks ago, a few weeks ago,
and I was talking about how the world is
is moving into this new space where
developers will continue to be creators.
We will We will be We'll do things in a
different way. And one of those ways is
we will look more into specifications,
less about code.
Exactly.
A developer came up to me though at the
end.
Okay.
And my last slide was, cuz it was Devops
UK, it was keep calm keep calm and carry
on cuz we as developers need need to
need to change.
Evolve evolve.
He was he was super worried though. He
was like, how can you put that slide up
when it means we're not looking at code.
He was he loves coding.
Yeah yeah yeah.
He absolutely like he his his safe space
was clearly in an IDE looking through
code. His mind was extremely technical,
loves the challenges, loves the depth.
So
those people deal with that?
So so I think when I say like we don't
want to look at code, we mostly don't
want to look at code which is not ours.
Like we're we're I mean we're humans.
We're selfish, we're self-centric. We
most of the time listen to someone and
then we listen the
what we really do is come up with a
clever reply to what they're about to
say without even listening. We know all
those flaws. Like humans are flawed. Um
and very self-centric. And this is true
about code as well. The example that I
gave you earlier I obviously love in
love with my code.
Yeah yeah.
But I'm much less inclined to look at
your code review because well okay
that's just some other code.
Yeah. Or or my code that's 1 month old.
Yeah. Which might as well be someone
else's code.
Absolutely. Right. So so and and this is
and this is the problem with the AI
generated code is someone else's code.
Yeah.
Right? So you might look at it and
especially now when it's a novelty, you
look at it out of curiosity to see what
the LLM does.
Yeah.
And you're like, oh my god this is
brilliant or this is crap. But but you
you look at it because you're curious.
Yeah.
Like in in in 6 months when more and
more code will be generated by AI,
you'll just
okay someone else's code.
Yeah yeah yeah.
Right? So so first of all you don't want
to look at this code. And obviously the
non-technical people definitely don't
want to look at this code.
They want to look at intent. They
they want to look at this test does this
and I can read that.
Exactly exactly. Right? And and and
generally the idea that code is that the
tests are technical and written in code,
I think, and that's just an assumption,
is one of the reasons why DDD really
didn't take over the world.
Because in the end of the day
DDD did you say that?
Yeah, like test-driven development
didn't take over the world because in
the end of the day if developers are the
only ones who can write the tests and
read the tests,
Yeah.
the real question becomes, at least for
me in my experience is, why am I doing
it this way?
Yeah.
I have a problem. I'm biased for action.
I know the solution in my I see
algorithms running code written in my
eyes. I want to go and write code. I
want to write tests. I don't mind write
tests afterwards to check that my code
does what it's supposed to do. But
starting with code doesn't make sense in
if developers are the only one involved
in the picture.
Yeah.
And I guess I'm not the only one who
thought about this problem. And this is
how one of the reasons why
behavioral-driven development came to be
20 years ago.
Yeah.
Like the BDD thing.
The way BDD works is like, "Hey, what if
the codes the the tests weren't defined
in code, but were defined in spec?"
Mhm.
And what BDD refers to spec is is some
kind of a
pseudo natural language. It's called
Gherkin and it's basically set of
rules that goes like, "Given context,
when something happened, then expect
those results."
Yeah.
Right? So, basically this is the this is
the steps. And the beauty of Gherkin
spec is that it's human readable.
Mhm.
Right? And the idea was that it's also
human writable. Right? So, the the
product managers, the business people,
maybe even the customer can participate
in writing those specs.
And it's interesting cuz when Agile came
in,
very often when we started writing use
cases and things like that and starting
with use cases, it was a similar Okay,
the language is slightly different, but
it was actually kind of a similar thing.
As a whoever, I want to do this with
Yeah.
Right. And and then the beauty of the
idea of Gherkin spec was that you take
an algorithm and compile those specs
into tests.
Mhm.
Now, look at us moving one step forward
toward building the integrity that we
spoke about. Because now, suddenly,
we can have something that technical
people and non-technical people together
can sit and write.
Yeah.
And then, if you remember the rest of
the chain that we started to build, the
spec is compiled to the test. We can
trust the test. That's exactly what the
spec was.
The code
implements the test.
So, we can trust the code because it has
to We have to because if it passes the
test, it does exactly what the test
want. And the tests are the result of
compilation of something that we agreed
our application should do.
So, the areas that you care about, you
should have as many of those tests as
you can. The areas that you don't care
about, you just allow the LLM to infer
whatever code it wants and whatever it
decides,
Yep.
that's the right way. That's That's a
way of doing it. That's an okay way.
If it's wrong, it means that you missed
some test that will enforce the way that
you want it. And it means that it missed
some spec. It missed some spec. It
misses one of those use cases of given
when then that you just need to go ahead
and write.
it's an uncaptured intent essentially.
Yeah.
Now,
BDD also didn't really take over the
world. We It's even You see it even less
than than TDD, actually. And again, my
speculation why is that
writing those structured
the structured intent the the
was still a little bit too much for the
non-technical people.
Mhm.
Right. Yes, of course, it's readable,
but writing it, it's kind of annoying.
Those are, you know, when you look at
the when you speak with business people
or product managers, they are kind of
free souls. They want to create. They
want to write Shakespeare. They don't
want to write this rigid like structure.
Yeah.
You you read PDDs, it's like it's like
poetry.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So, so again, those specs didn't really
catch up because
product managers like us, that's too
rigid. And then if they don't do it,
developers definitely not going to do
it.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right, because for some reason.
I also think I also think with the the
one of the issues with BDD is
there was no hard connection
between the the the the BDD intents, the
spec part, and anything else.
Yeah.
It was it was left up to someone to then
implement that. And as change happened
in the business and things like that, it
got stale.
It gets stale.
In the same way a PRD would. And then
all of a sudden, you no one goes back to
the PRD because it's out of date. The
code is the is the source of truth.
But now, if we automate all the way from
the spec to the end product,
the spec is very important, but no one
wants to write this Gherkin stupid
thing.
Yeah. Yeah.
Suddenly, AI can help.
Yeah.
Cuz we don't need to.
Mhm.
Right. Once we have a
like a specification document.
Yeah.
Right. Whatever you call it, software
definition document, whatever. There are
a bunch of We can ask AI to formulate
those specs,
Mhm.
those when given when then from it. Now,
we know that it will hallucinate.
Mhm.
And we know that the spec won't be
exactly as what we wanted it to do.
Mhm.
For mainly two reasons. The first is I
mentioned it hallucinates. But the
second is that it's very hard for humans
to express um
intent in the words.
Yeah.
Uh, because of context that we have in
our heads that obviously LLM lacks. So,
there is this chasm between the prompt
and the intent
between what we ask it to do and what we
really wanted it to do.
Yes.
So, for those two reasons, the spec
won't be perfect.
Mhm.
But,
coming back to the biggest benefit of
the spec, because it is readable,
we can actually review it.
Yes.
It's different from tests that we
theoretically also could declare a
source of truth and review it instead of
specs. But, as we spoke, we don't want
to read anyone else's code and
especially the non-technical people that
they even cannot.
Yeah.
Spec is different
because it's readable
Mhm.
in your language. There are hundreds of
languages translations of Gherkin spec.
You can,
uh, read it in Urdu if you feel like.
Mhm.
Uh, and
And
this is suddenly something that
everybody, um,
around the table
can sync on
Yeah.
and say, "Okay, now we can read the
spec. It's not painful in English. And
we can verify that what's in spec it's
actually what we wanted to be generated
from our prompt.
Yeah.
Now, if it's not, we go back and forth,
we iterate until it is, or we just fix
the spec. It's It's almost plain
language.
And And presumably you could almost like
use LLM as a judge as well to some
extent almost to as a as a
as a final backup to say, "Look, cuz
because people are going to be lazy,
right?"
And And I think this is one of those
interesting things where even if you
look at something like code review.
Mhm.
Okay, people don't like looking at each
other's
at someone else's code, for example, but
it's something that,
um,
the more text, the more change there is,
we'll kind of like look at that and go,
"Yeah, that that kind of like looks
good." If there's two lines, we're going
All right, we're going to we're going to
be questioning the variable choices and
things like that, right?
So so if there is going to be a big set
of tests or a big specification, are we
actually going to go through it? An LLM
as a judge could actually be There there
are going to be levels of automation
that okay
it we need that backup almost. So
there's potentially two levels there.
One for the human
bring different models. We can generate
specs with one model and then ask
another model if it thinks that the
intent is being captured.
Yes. Yeah.
Right. And then it can we can iterate
and make this process. And then but the
in the end of the day
human-readable specs are much easier to
review than tests or code. Right? And
this is like the main idea. So now we
have the entire chain.
We start with the prompt. Like, "Hey, I
want to write an application that does
ABC. Come up with the set of specs
that will satisfy those requirements."
Then we have the specs. We don't trust
the LLM. So
the problem with LLM that
it is non-deterministic
better than random code generator.
Right? So my analogy
I like that.
My analogy is you remember this
thought experiment that if you give to
endless number of monkeys endless
number of typewriters eventually they
will come with the works of Shakespeare.
This is LLMs. They are slightly better
than random monkeys typing on
typewriters, but eventually that's
exactly that. They try to get it right
and it almost sometimes almost works.
All right? So and and and the idea is
that you cannot really trust a monkey to
write Shakespeare specially not on the
first run. So the the idea here is that
I think that's the that's the that's the
quote that we should take out from this
entire podcast. You can't trust a monkey
to write Shakespeare.
This is exactly
thing.
care whether you're spec-driven,
spec-centric, code-centric. That's one
thing we can all agree on.
Never trust a monkey to write
Shakespeare.
Or any kind of famous literature, I'd
say.
Or or code.
Yeah, or code. Well, some I've seen some
code.
No, but that's but
seen some code, but it wasn't
Shakespeare.
No, that's true. Absolutely not, yeah.
So, let's make sure that we iterate
until it is. Yeah. And that's exactly
the idea, right? So, the monkeys
generate spec. Will they do it right
from the first time? Probably not. We
want to bring other monkeys and and
eventually the most important is we'll
look at the spec and we say, "Well, it
rhymes, but it's not Shakespeare."
Yeah.
Try it again with slightly different
prompt.
Yeah.
Or we can just add the spec directly.
Mhm.
Now, once we have the spec, we say,
"Okay, we cannot trust the monkey to
generate correct tests from the spec
because we cannot trust the monkey."
Yeah.
Now, the problem is that we decided
we're not going to review the the tests.
Mhm.
Too much for us. It's someone else's
code. We don't want to do it. The the
beauty of a namely Cucumber, but but
generally parsable spec
Mhm.
is that we don't need a monkey.
Yeah.
Because we take an algorithm and compile
the specs into tests deterministically
every time.
Yeah. So, if you do it
need the monkey.
If you run it 10 times, you'll get the
same thing 10 times. Whereas, if you do
it with LLMs, there'll be subtle
differences and maybe sometimes
and since we don't review the test, we
won't even know that something is wrong.
Yeah.
Right? So, monkey's out of the picture
for this part.
Mhm.
Right? So, we generate the test. Now,
once we have the tests, we can let
monkeys loose,
Mhm.
type on those typewriters forever until
the tests pass.
Yeah.
The only thing is we need to protect the
tests
Yeah.
because the monkeys will be inclined to
adjust the test to make them pass.
Yeah.
So, how do you do it?
Whatever. Make the files read-only. Put
them in a Docker container and make them
unaccessible like also read-only.
Yeah.
Do whatever to protect the tests and
then let the monkeys loose. Let them
type
as long as they want to
until the test pass.
Yeah.
And now
we have the chain.
Mhm.
Right? We have a prompt
that is
guaranteed
to capture
our intent
Mhm.
because we reviewed the specs.
Yeah.
And then we have the code that is
guaranteed to match the specs because we
generated code we generated tests
without the monkeys and then the the
code
actually passes the tests. So, we can
have the entire picture from our
ideation to the end product that we can
absolutely 100% trust. This is an intent
integrity chain because we guarantee the
integrity of our intent
Mhm.
in the code.
Okay. So, let's say now that we release
that.
Yep.
The world is wonderful.
We have we have farms of both cucumbers
and monkeys, okay? In in separate cages
and in separate in separate fields and
and forests.
Um
now
someone comes in and says, "I want to
make a change."
Beautiful.
Right.
We have maybe there's some bug changes,
maybe there's some feature changes,
maybe there's new features that need
Yep.
to be added. What does that What does
that flow look like? How do you How do
we stop the monkeys from attacking the
cucumbers?
So, I will mention now a word that you
expect the least.
Microservices.
Okay.
Yeah.
What What
Yeah, I could I could have said several
words before you had to said
microservices then, but go ahead.
The The intent integrity chain,
microservices it's its best friend.
Mhm.
Because once your code is modular enough
and the services are micro enough, you
know what you do? You throw it away.
You You You go. There is a new
requirement or there is a bug. You go
back to the beginning. You go to the
prompt. You fix this prompt to include
this feature or to express your intent
better. You run the process all over
again and you have a new service that
will replace the old one
and you're good to go.
So, I wouldn't have said Microsoft Well,
maybe it is Microsoft's. It's
It's huge composability to the extreme
whereby when something changes,
actually, there's a component or a
number of components that just need to
be Well, in fact, it comes to that stage
whereby you don't You don't throw it
away in the sense that this code is
never usable again cuz other things
might rely on it, I suppose. But you
would find something else that that does
that job in a different way and use that
or or add that in. Yeah.
And And you define APIs and they are
very easily definable in prompt and back
and test. And then, once you have the
the API defined, every part is
replaceable. So, you can actually
replace every component with a better
version of this component because you
improved the prompt. The code is
absolutely disposable. It's garbage to
begin with. It's monkeys wrote it. It is
garbage. And we And no one even looked
at it ever because we don't care as long
as the test pass.
So So So, okay, here's a new feature
brief. What are you changing? What's
What What What is the document you're
changing?
So, we start with the prompt. We always
start with the prompt. So, the prompt is
some reference to a software definition
document that product managers probably
maintain. So, we change this software
definition document and our prompt will
be like, "Hey, we have additions
and let's do the entire thing again."
So, that changes a spec.
That changes That changes the spec.
Do you Do you
In your vision, do you break the spec
down so you so you have that that you
know spec down?
you can go tons of different directions,
right? You can say, "Okay, our spec
should be very small and limited scope,
so we can easily replace it." You can
say, "Okay, our spec should be modular,
so we can
we can direct prompt to change only part
of it." Uh you can say, "You know what?
The small is the change is so small, I
won't even bother with generating new
specs. I'm just going to edit the spec."
Yeah.
There is like one sentence that I need
to change. It's easier for me to just
change than go through the entire
prompting. It doesn't matter. In the end
of the day, what you need to make sure
is that the spec this is your source of
truth.
Yeah.
Right? Because again, it's still
readable by all the humans. We can agree
on it and iterate of it if needed. And
if it's too hard for us to to write it,
we can use LLM to generate it, and it's
completely fine. We But in the end of
the day, what we all
agree upon will be the spec.
Yeah.
And we evolve it as as we see
fit. Replace it, edit it, regenerate it,
or do whatever we like with it.
And how good is And I'm going to be
honest, I haven't used Cucumber in like
I was I was going to say years, I'm
going to say decades.
This is why we're old.
So, yeah, this is why we're old.
The benefit of being old, I dug up
something that new generation has no
idea that they exist.
Yeah. Yeah. Or even if you say BDD, most
people will go, "What What's a BDD? Is
that like a Is that a new TDD?" Um so,
how good is Cucumber at change on
something that exists? So, Cucumber turn
something into existing, would you just
redo the whole thing?
So, the idea is that you redo the whole
thing, right? And this is why having the
code smaller and modular is so
important. Not only that it's it's it's
important for Cucumber or not, but
remember that we don't look at the code.
Yeah.
So, if we try to refactor something, we
actually don't know if it's any good and
if it does what we wanted it to do.
Yeah.
We need new updated set of of tests.
That we don't
look either.
Yeah.
The only thing that we do look are are
the specs.
Uh-huh.
So, once we change the specs, we have to
regenerate everything down this down the
road because that's the only way to
guarantee that it actually matches the
spec.
Yeah.
And then the code matches the test and
then everything else works with the
chain.
Yeah.
Right. Now, so Cucumber is just an idea.
This is what I had in my
It exists. It exists and yeah, yeah.
And obviously Gherkin specs are not
perfect because frankly there are
concepts that are impossible to describe
in Given-When-Then.
Mhm.
For example, security constraints.
Right. You can do something with
performance. You can write a spec that
will kind of express like given a
certain load ex- like when you throw
more users, then the application
responds in under a time, but it also it
already starts to be awkward.
Mhm. Mhm.
And and especially stuff like other
non-functional requirements like
security, it's it's impossible to
express.
Yeah.
Right. Because the the the whole idea of
behavioral driven development is to
express behavior and cross
non-functional concerns are are hard to
express as behavior.
Mhm.
So, obviously
it was never intended to use for for for
this kind of stuff and the only way the
only
like reason why I demonstrated with
Gherkin and Cucumber because it's it's
it's just here.
Yeah.
But what if
what if we had a better way to express
the spec?
Mhm.
Something that is born for AI,
born for this kind of problem that
intended chain doesn't change.
Yeah.
You only have a better tool in this part
when you need to go from spec to code.
Yes.
Everything else remains the same. You
still have the same concerns of never
trust a monkey and how do we make sure
that our intent is properly captured,
how do we close the chasm between prompt
and intent, all those problems and the
concept that solves them is the same. We
will just have a better implementation
for the part that goes from spec to
code.
Really interesting. Uh it's that
hardening, really, isn't it? It's that
hardening and it's not going to happen,
unfortunately, the way LLMs are trained.
Yeah.
We're not going to get that hardening in
most likely.
We never, because the whole idea of an
LLM is that it's by definition
non-deterministic. That's the whole
idea, right? So, you probably know and
probably most of your audience for I
native knows
how how it works, like the neural
networks, that they have to have this
level of freedom
Yeah.
in order to generate something that is
different than what it has been asked.
It needs to guess the
what the
reply should be
that is related to what you asked, but
not exactly what you asked because then
it's just useless.
Yeah.
So, it has to have this
degree of freedom. It has to be
stochastic by non-deterministic by
definition. And when you play with the
temperature of the network and how
creative it is, this is the balance of
if it's the temperature is too high, it
will hallucinate more. If it is too low,
you won't get the responses that you
want from it because you limit how much
it can go in search for the right
answer. But, and regardless of the
temperature that you set,
unless it's zero, which makes the model
absolutely unusable, you will have
non-deterministic behavior built in. So,
the idea of not trusting the monkey will
never go away.
Because it will
generate different replies for your
request, and only one of them will be
the right one. So, the rest of them by
definition will be a wrong one.
And other than I guess resources being
used, overly used.
It's actually not a problem that we
don't trust the monkey because of the
the framework and the the guardrails
that we've added.
Exactly. Exactly. And we will let it
type non-Shakespeare until Shakespeare
emerges.
Yeah. Yeah. Cuz the rest is just throw.
Yeah. Exactly.
So, okay. We've talked about a
technology that is, oh my god, like 30
years old probably
in Cucumber and Gherkin Spec and things
like that. Let's project forward now.
Okay. In this vision, in this in this
projected way of that we will build
apps. I guess two questions. We'll start
with the SDLC and then we'll go on to
the what a developer is. SDLC, how would
that need to change?
So, in the end of the day, we are
speaking here about a pretty narrow area
of proper code of of of code generation,
right? Of how can we trust the generated
code? Now, there is like the entire um
chain
that oh
of of of writing of of delivering
software that is
after that, all the sure the the the
build and everything else. Now, this all
can obviously
be improved by using the AI, but this is
kind of a a little bit out of scope for
the intent integrity chain in
particular, mostly because most of it is
already kind of algorithmic, right? So,
the build is a completely algorithmic
problem. The only thing that can change
is now, and this is the beauty of it and
that's the raising the level of
obstruction and this is the evolution
that you spoke about the keynote is that
you can look at everything after the
spec
as a part of the build.
Yeah.
Right in the end of the day
we took the spec that the spoken word
the written word
and compiled it into working Java code
or
whatever other code
and then the build compiles it even
further to
the
whatever machine
uh
To liquid software.
Yeah, exactly. Right? And then and then
from there it goes to and and and and
being deployed on whatever. So, we kind
of made a compiler out of a
non-deterministic system. Very wasteful
but also very fun. Right? Which feeds
another compiler that compiles to byte
code which feeds another system that
puts it on like data centers and what
So, so eventually
it's all compilers down there
Yeah.
from the spec.
Uh-huh.
So, spec becomes our
Yeah.
programming language and everything else
is just LDLT.
And so that then leads us onto that next
question of I guess this So, this Let's
break this down into two now in terms of
developers. I guess the scope of who can
be a developer
broadens and diversifies.
Absolutely.
What about the developer of today? What
what would you see So, first of all let
me ask you the question that that first
question.
What does a developer look like in 5-10
years?
So,
for me what's really not going away and
I don't think it will ever is the
expertise.
Yeah.
And the expertise for us is what uh can
can called
like ga
grasping the art of the possible
in computer engineering or computer
science.
Because if you let non-technical people
write the prompts and then read the
specs, it can be absolutely wildly
unconceivable in terms of machine
implementation.
Yeah.
The requirements might be absolutely uh
uh unrealistic.
Yeah.
In terms of functional requirements, but
also in terms of non-functional
requirements, uh like performance uh
requirements that can never be met.
Mhm.
Right? Or or anything like that.
But are these things that can be learned
by non-technical people? I mean, like
there's no reason
Well, to an extent, right? They can
learn by kind of observing that, "Hey,
this is not possible. We don't really
understand why."
Yeah.
But the technical people ask, "We do
understand why." Which gives us
much more abilities to be this So, we
have like the the imaginary table that
we have all the stakeholders, which is
the business, the customers, the
product, security people, and everybody
else have a say when they read those
specs. And the let's say someone says,
"Well, we need to make this application
taste faster."
Yeah.
And and us as developers sitting on the
table, this is where we say, "No, we
actually cannot."
Yes.
And this is why.
Yeah.
And instead, we need to go the other
route and re-architect or something in
order to make it happen.
So, the architect is That's interesting.
It's It's It's the level of abstraction
is lifted to an architecture question.
And so, you have certain developers
there that care about the architecture
and certain developers
We were talking about previously was
that people who care more about that
intent.
Yes.
That I need this to do this.
They're they're providing that input and
it's the it's the person who's more on
that architecture side that says, "Okay,
I can I can help you get to this stage
by making these changes."
Yes. And then there is a lot of
technical expertise that gets into it
because people can say, "Okay, now you
you have this service that you want to
generate, but it actually too wide, so
it will be very resource
very wasteful on resources to regenerate
it every time that you have a change
request. So, we might want to make it
small. So, it's not only about
understanding what the end
application should do, it's also
understanding about how the intended
integrity check works and what needs to
go to the code and what's not. And this
is not different from what we do today.
Right? We have opinions on both the
quality of the code itself. Well, this
variable is not properly named or this
should be refactored in this way or or
or that. And we have opinions about the
architecture of our application. Well,
this is
should be designed this way or those
components should talk to each other and
don't and those do not. This all
translates.
Yes.
It just translates a little bit
differently. So, that whoever really
cares about the greedy details of the
implementation might be interested in
the implementation of the intended
integrity check mechanism of this
compiler of compilers. And whoever cares
about more about architecture will still
care about architecture. They will just
discuss it not in terms of interface
names and implementation classes names,
but in terms of the specs and how the
microservices talking to each other or
not talking to each other.
Yeah.
Right? So, the expertise the technical
expertise that we have is still
absolutely critical for software
engineering. This is not going away.
Yeah.
And the knowledge the domain knowledge
is suddenly even more important.
Yeah. Yeah.
Before we wrap up, let me ask you back.
Oh, okay.
Right. So, Tessell.
Yes.
It's about spec.
Mhm.
So, this is it sounds to me that when I
told that I told told you that, you know
what wouldn't be wonderful if we had
something better to capture the spec and
then translate it to code.
It sounds like you might have something
that might
fit into this piece that is not exactly
missing, but I would say not perfect in
the intent integrity chain.
Yeah, I I think this is kind of like at
the core of what we're looking at in
terms of, you know, we believe that this
kind of like spec-centric world is going
to be is going to be the place that that
you know, with the validation, with the
checks and that and that feedback loop,
uh we are in a better place to actually
be able to say, this is what we want.
Yeah.
And then allow LLM to kind of like fill
in the gaps, but then test is again,
like we're very similar to the the so
much that you said that resonates. Test
becomes the most important thing.
Um
code is essentially a disposable
artifact that can be generated, but as
long as your tests are good, your your
your code will be proven good enough.
Exactly.
Um and I think when you talk about the
componentization and things like that,
this all resonates very very much.
So, let's do let's do a fun experiment.
Yeah.
A talk to me in intent integrity chain
with Tessell. How it will work? The
process when we replace the 20-years-old
and not really fitting technology with
something that was born for the AI age.
I know I'm a product manager. I don't
read or understand code. I have a
software definition document
Yeah. which beautiful piece of
literature and I want it in code with
intent integrity chain with Tesla
inside. How does it work?
So, I think I think there's there's
three key things that are important to
be able to describe. One key thing is
whatever whatever things that we want
this to be able to do. This this
whatever it is to be able to do.
Capabilities are really cool there. To
be able to describe this is the set of
capabilities that I want this unit of
software this you know software
component to be able to
And I can ask a LLM
Yep.
to take the my beautiful literature of
software definition document
and describe those capabilities for
Tesla.
Yep.
Okay, got it.
The the next most important thing
is tests.
Right.
Okay? And we see tests the way we're
looking at it is tests are actually part
of that specification. So, we actually
say per capability, well, what are the
what are the the the the groups the
areas that that we that we assert need
to be true or you know
negatively
need to be true in order for that to in
order for that to to to to be realized.
And this still tracks with the spec
generation that we spoke about. Still
LLM will review my software definition
document and will come with list of
capabilities
Yeah.
and the test criteria or test scenarios
for those capabilities and we as humans
everybody product manager business
technical people will review this and
will say, well, that's not exactly what
I meant. Let me adjust something in the
document and regenerate all of that or
maybe just edit
edit it right there.
Yeah.
And tweak it. Okay. Now, we have
capabilities. We have the test
descriptions test scenarios.
The third the third thing though cuz
this composability is super interesting.
So, the third thing is being able to
say, "This is the API. This is This is
how I would describe this component to
others."
Right.
So, that you allow for that, you know,
Microservices and interchangeability.
Exactly. Exactly. Yep. And I think the
API is a great actual way of actually
saying to the LLM, "This is the intent
at which I want this component to be
used." So, you're actually describing
the interactions as well as the
capabilities, which is which is which is
very very important.
Right. And this is the the third part of
this
amorphic spec.
Yeah.
And and
most of those parts you kind of can
describe with Gherkin, but not really.
Especially not the API. And and and and
this is where we have much more powerful
tool to describe those specs.
Yeah. Yeah.
Now, I think the I think the interesting
thing that we see now as a as a
potential future is whereby that spec
tests can be generated, code can be
generated. But But the important thing
is there is a level of context that can
then be added, which is outside of the
spec, cuz the spec could describe the
you know, the behavior, but it doesn't
actually describe the pure
implementation as much. Whereas the
context can say, "These are the things
that I care about." It could be
language. It could be performance
requirements. It could be stack. It
could be It could be the availability
that was required.
Accessibility.
Whatever. I I I tell
the things like that.
And and all those pieces are exactly
what we miss from the intelligent direct
based on Cucumber, because
the the when it's based on Cucumber,
it's behavior only.
Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
And I think that then allows you to have
one spec with multiple versions of this
implementation that can like come out.
That and it's all compilers down there.
Yeah.
Beautiful.
Also, let's say there's a security
issue.
Yeah.
Or a bug.
Does that actually require Sometimes
that's just based in the implementation
that we won't find till later. Perhaps a
test is missing or something like that.
Or a a new vulnerability, like a
third-party vulnerability has been been
found. Is that a change to your
implementation?
Or is that a change to your spec? Nine
times out of 10 I feel like it's not a
spec change. Very often
Okay, there's a bug in the way this was
implemented. We need to make sure we're
using this version or this or No, that
kind of thing.
With with the original intended target
to change that it's still a problem.
Yeah.
Because we don't read the code.
We don't read the tests.
Yeah.
We definitely don't read the whatever
like build scripts that dictate the
versions. So, yes, theoretically we can
write something like Yeah, but
when this is used, use like Spring Boot
3.5 and not 3.4. But this is very
awkward because it's completely foreign
for the idea of behavioral driven. It's
not It doesn't describe a behavior.
But on the
if I have multiple of these being
created and stacks being created, I
don't want everything to use completely
different stacks or just choose various
languages and things like that. At some
point I'm going to want to say remain
consistent because it it reduces my
attack surface, it reduces the the the
effort I need to then stand all of that
up. So, I might say actually, for
consistency reason, this is the stack I
choose, these are the languages I
choose, etc.
As a result, I want consistency between
my components, between my applications.
So,
and yeah, that isn't necessarily
something you want to add in at the
spec. It's actually an implementation
detail because if I want if I want
behavioral changes, I go to my spec. If
I then want the deployment changes or
implementation changes, I need to change
the context with which this is
generated.
And and this is again like a missing
piece in what I described, but if we
take Tesla instead this
spec to code part, then we can add those
non-behavioral concerns
in a native way that you envisioned
Mhm.
and then it makes it even more usable
and you don't need to abuse the spec for
stuff that is not really intended.
you almost pollute it a little bit,
right? And so you you have that you have
that distinction. One of the things that
I do love in this model is this is this
loop.
Yep.
Uh
And and this loop goes, you know, we
talk about that kind of like the the the
the SDLC and then it will go into
production. There are so many places at
which you can loop, whether that's
quality tests, whether that's
performance tests, whether all the way
through to observability data in
production and pulling that pulling that
useful information back that we can
actually pass into that into the
generation.
Yep.
And the value is we, you know, with that
with that validation verification all
the way through to say does it still
adhere to the spec? Does it still adhere
to the things that that is is is cared
about by the stakeholders, by the people
who are actually describing it. So, as
long as that is well described and the
things you care about are documented
there, you can iterate through and you
can just let it go go wild.
Exactly.
you know, get those monkeys going. Let's
let's let's loop loop loop loop until
the specification and it's core that we
always constantly check with that
specification is is satisfied but also
you know, these these tweaks and changes
are made to satisfy the non-functional,
to satisfy the business needs, etc. So,
I think it's a it's a super powerful
space.
And and and and here you have it's a
it's a win-win, right? So, intended
integrity chain but implemented with
something much more powerful than just
BDD.
Yeah.
Covers those
uh areas that kind of the uncomfortable
questions that I have to this model.
Yeah.
Like, what do you do with security? What
do you do with specification details
that you care about but you still don't
want to read code and this kind of stuff
and it's a it's a beautiful win-win.
Yeah. Well, beautiful win-win. That's
that's where that's where we leave it,
man.
That's that's who we that's what we do.
Great. It's been a pleasure.
I'm looking forward to the rest of AI
focus. So, yeah. Thanks very much.
Thanks very much for listening and uh be
sure to tune in to the next episode.
Yep. Thank you. Bye-bye.